*music*
Well, good morning. I'd like to welcome you all. I have seen so many old faces back today. Evelyn's here.
Anxious. So old. Myron's back. Al, obviously, you're here frequently, but it's really good to see all you guys again.
If you're new here, we really welcome you. I'd like to welcome everybody to the first of our six-week series on Ephesians.
Yay! So six weeks on Ephesians, six chapters. We're going to cover roughly one chapter a week.
But it's important to understand we're not just going to cover the chapter. We're not digging down because the themes of Ephesians run side to side.
The whole book needs to be taken in strong context. It's a letter. It's a single letter.
And so each week we're going to cover a theme that, you know, kind of runs through the breadth of the book and then examine it in that chapter.
So that's the way we're going to approach this. Feel free to read the whole letter each week for the next six weeks.
Did my mic just cut out? No, we're good. Okay, great.
So the theme that we're going to focus on today is best exemplified in the Lord's Prayer.
We just read it together. It ends,
Your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
Yours is the kingdom, the power and the glory forever.
That kingdom phrase, right, is Your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
And then it sounds, I think many of us read it like there's a laundry list that comes next.
And I want a pony.
There's a, you know, what's next? Who can tell me?
Daily bread, right.
Give us the day our daily bread.
Forgive us our sins.
Temptation, evil, right.
All these things we'd like to have happen.
But I think it would be useful for you if you recognize that His kingdom come, His will be done.
Those next four things happen, right?
That's sort of not a laundry list of other things you'd like.
That's a descriptor of what it's like in the kingdom of heaven, right?
Give us this day our daily bread.
Give us the sustenance we need to live by, the basics of life.
We're asking, it's a world without scarcity.
We're not beset by the troubles of scarcity.
And I don't mean you have everything you want.
I mean, it's your daily bread.
In the kingdom of God, your needs are provided for, right?
The next one is, forgive us as we forgive those who trespass against us, right?
Forgive us our sins.
Because we recognize that we're in that kingdom of heaven through God's gracious forgiveness,
unwarranted forgiveness that allows us freedom from the consequences of our sins
and the freedom from sin controlling our lives.
And we're so grateful for that that it overflows to the next person.
So this is a kingdom, a domain in which there's no vengeance, right?
We're not passing on unforgiveness to the next person.
We're passing on forgiveness to the next person.
So it's a place not beset by the trials of scarcity.
It's a place not beset by the trials of vengeance and unforgiveness.
It's not beset by temptation.
It's not beset by evil.
So these are descriptors of the kingdom of heaven that we're praying for.
God, please let that happen.
When your kingdom comes, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
So this was what Paul is writing to the Ephesians about, right?
Ephesus is right there.
It's on the nose of Turkey.
It's a large port city.
And all the trade routes ran through Ephesus.
So if you wanted to deliver a circular letter, it would be passed around to all the churches.
Ephesus is the place you send it.
And then we're told that Tychicus, this delivery guy, would carry it around.
And he would explain the letter to people.
So it's a descriptor to all the churches in the area of what it looks like when you enter into the kingdom of heaven.
That's what the letter of the Ephesians is.
It's the same, how do I want to see the kingdom of heaven in Ephesus as it is in heaven?
And that's why we have these shirts in Winchester as it is in heaven, right?
The kingdom of God in Winchester as it is in heaven is what we want.
So with that in mind, let's just, I'm going to read through the first chapter of Ephesians with you today.
We don't need to stand and read it together.
I'm almost certainly going to interrupt a lot.
And we will talk about it after we've read through it once, okay?
So.
Starts Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God.
Paul, an apostle, is someone who delivers an epistle.
Apostle is a messenger.
So I'm a formal messenger of Christ Jesus.
Christ is the Messiah, the Jewish Messiah by the will of God.
So the word he used there.
So Paul says as an opening line, just, I don't want this to flitter past you because you read it quickly like it's just an intro.
Paul opens his letter saying, the creator God of the universe had the Jewish Messiah tell me to bring you this message, right?
That's his opening sentence.
It's a significant thing that should have weighed heavily on the people that were shocked to hear it, right?
That Paul, he's an apostle sent by the Messiah by the will of God.
Okay.
To the saints who are in Ephesus and who are faithful in Christ Jesus.
Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
And then Paul launches into a sentence that lasts down until verse 14.
Okay.
The rest of this chapter has two sentences in it in the Greek.
Because Paul is just spewing forth dense thought.
He's just feeding them from the fire hose with something that he's desperate to get all the nuance into.
Okay.
So when you read this, don't break it into little phrases.
This is all one big thought.
Okay.
Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ who blessed us in Christ.
Blessed be God who blessed us in Christ.
For with every spiritual blessing in heavenly places, even as he chose us before the foundation of the world,
that we should be holy and blameless before him in love, predestined us for adoption to himself as sons through Jesus Christ,
according to the purpose of his will, to the praise of his glorious grace, with which he has blessed us in the beloved.
In him we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace,
which he lavished upon us in wisdom and insight, making known to us the mystery of his will,
according to his purpose, which he set forth in Christ as a plan for the fullness of time to unite all things in him in heaven and things on earth.
So there you see that theme, things in heaven and things on earth united.
Your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
And you being in verse, we have been redemption, redemption and forgiveness of our sins in verse seven, right?
Forgive us our sins as we forgive those who trespass against us.
These are the themes that Paul's hitting.
You should, the pronouns hopefully stood out to you when I was reading that, right?
He's talking about we and you and us, right?
And he's talking about inheritance and adoption, right?
So what's he talking about there and why is he saying it?
Well, who is the, what are we adopted, who is predestined in verse five?
Everyone's predestined to what in this letter?
Adoption, right?
You're predestined to be adopted.
And who is it that's predestined to be adopted?
Well, you, right?
So the letter's written to you, which is the faithful in Christ, right?
And we also see in chapter two, verse 11, that they are specifically the Gentiles.
So Paul's written this, writing this letter to Gentiles who are faithful in Christ.
There's known elsewhere in the Old, in the New Testament as God-fearing Gentiles.
So these are Gentiles who have decided to follow the Jewish Messiah.
And because they've been faithful, it says, they are adopt, predestined into adoption.
Well, what's that adoption?
The other person is written to, the we.
You as the Gentiles, who's the we Paul's talking about, right?
In verse 13, it says, in him, you also have heard the word of truth, the gospel of salvation,
and believed were sealed in the promise of the Holy Spirit.
That's the God-fearing Gentiles.
In verse 12, we who were first to hope in Christ might be to the praise of the glory.
Who were the first people to believe in the Jewish Messiah?
It's not a strict question.
Jewish, right, yeah.
So Paul, he's saying, we first had this hope.
The Jews had known forever that the world would be blessed through them, through the Messiah
that would come, and he would set up this kingdom on earth, right?
And he's saying, we first had this hope.
And we had always been predestined to be adopted into this kingdom that was coming.
That was the promise we were given by God.
And now you, because of your faithfulness into Christ, you're following the Messiah,
you also have joined us in this promise of adoption, right?
That's what he's saying in verse 1, all in one sentence, because he's writing this to Gentiles
who don't have this perspective.
They didn't grow up Jewish, right?
So he's trying to communicate to them that they are now with him in the thing,
which we know in chapter 2 that the law has been used in their church as, what does he call it?
He calls it a dividing wall of hostility, right?
Because the Jews had put all these commandments around the law to keep from breaking the law
because they were so worried about breaking the law.
Probably heard of this.
And Paul says, well, that's now, since Christ has come, the Christ who you follow,
and he's fulfilled the law, all those commandments aren't necessary.
And all these things that are creating a hostile division between the Gentiles and the Jews in the church,
they go away.
What matters is what it looks like in the kingdom of heaven.
And that's what he's trying to convey in this first statement.
It's just this burbling statement that, hey, you and we are now us,
and we're adopted together, right?
Verse 15, for this reason, for what reason?
The thing he just said, right?
Because we're together in this adoption.
Because we have a common inheritance now in this kingdom of God.
For this reason, because I have heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus
and your love toward the saints.
Incidentally, the love toward the saints is probably that they actually gave financially.
Paul was always taking up an offering for the people that are being persecuted, mainly in Jerusalem.
And, you know, they physically showed their love to these saints that were in a far land, right?
For this reason, because I have heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus
and your love toward all the saints,
I do not cease to give thanks for you,
remembering you in my prayers.
And then he begins to give a sample of some of the things he prays, right?
That the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of all glory,
may give you the spirit of wisdom and revelation and knowledge of him,
having the eyes for your hearts to be enlightened.
That's four things.
Wisdom, enlightenment.
He wants them to know something, right?
He's really highlighting.
I want you to know things.
This is the purpose of the letter, right?
He's jumping right into it.
What does he want them to know and be enlightened about and have wisdom to understand?
And in verse 5, that you may know what is the hope to which he's called you.
I'm sorry, verse 18.
The hope to which he's called you.
The riches of his glorious inheritance in the saints.
And what's the immeasurable greatness of his power toward those who believe?
A hope, an inheritance, and power.
That's what he wants them to know about.
What's that power?
In verse 19, the power toward those who believe according to the works of his might,
of his great might, that he worked in Christ when he raised him from the dead
and seated him at his right hand in heavenly places.
That's a significant power, right?
Raising from the dead, seating in heaven, almost unbelievable power, right?
So this hope you have in a kingdom of God that's going to be placed on earth,
that can be substantiated by a significant power, right?
And I want you to understand that you have an inheritance in that.
So, whatever your picture of heaven is, we understand that heaven will be when we're with God.
And I believe it's easier to have the faith that God will someday just wipe out the evil
and whisk us away to where he is, right?
Because it's miraculous.
We just believe he has the power to do it.
And it's easy to envision.
And we don't really know what heaven would be like.
We know it would be with God.
But however we picture it, we know it's an approximation.
It's an analogy.
Because we don't know what that's like.
But what it says in the Lord's Prayer is,
your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
So whatever our picture of heaven is, there's some component of this that's on earth.
And that's a lot harder to sort of just trust in.
Because we see our neighbors.
And we see into our own heart.
And we see the news.
And we know that there's injustice.
We know there are people that are abusing power.
We know there's violence beset by people who are greedy and misusing language and law
to call what's evil good and good evil.
We know that there's a great difficulty just in our own heart to ever act without pride.
And to ever not betray someone when it's in our self-interest to do so.
All these things do not feel like a kingdom of heaven.
And so for God to come in and make heaven in the midst of all that,
that seems really difficult to us.
Because we see all those individual problems.
But what we're talking about here, and what he's describing to the Ephesians here,
is how they're going to live in this kingdom of heaven on earth.
Some sort of footprint.
Some sort of outpost of the kingdom of heaven.
I'm just going to keep reading.
And Christ then is the power that raised Christ from the dead can make this happen.
And verse 21, he's seated at the right hand of God in heavenly places,
far above rule and authority and power and dominion,
and above every name that's named, not only in this age but in the ones to come.
These people are citizens or subjects of the Roman Empire.
If you think racism is bad in America,
you should read some of the accounts of how minorities were treated in the Roman Empire.
It's shocking that there was not a constant uprising.
And the reason there wasn't a constant uprising was because of the heavy-handed Roman soldiers.
The Roman army was indomitable.
So they're living in a place where there is no justice unless you're a Roman citizen, right?
They're living in a place where there's constant strife and all the evidence that there's not a kingdom of heaven on earth.
And yet, they're into this, right?
They're hearing him and they believe it.
So we need to come back and ask ourselves why that is.
But what Paul is telling them is that Christ has been placed far above all those authorities that they know,
the Roman authorities, and all the powers and dominions, the pagan gods that they'd served,
who were capricious and angry gods, right?
They had to be appeased constantly as far as they understood it.
Hard to understand how they worked.
And he's saying, no, no, there's a God who was a laborer like you.
He was a minority, probably like you.
He lived in a small outpost of the Roman Empire like you.
He was subjected to the vagaries and the violence of the Roman soldiers.
In fact, he was crucified by them.
And he is now placed in heaven above all those authorities, all those dominions, all those powers, right?
This is a shocking statement.
This would be an amazing statement to an oppressed minority somewhere in the Roman Empire in the midst of Turkey around Ephesus, okay?
And he has put all things under his feet, under Jesus' feet, and given him a head over all things.
He's now head of the church, which is his body, the fullness of him who fills all in all.
And so he's just said, the church, you people that are faithful in Christ, are his body on earth, right?
He's your head, you're the body.
You're a part of this organic thing.
That's two long sentences, right?
The first one, to tell them who they are, because Paul knows that behavior flows from identity.
So the first thing he's telling them is who they are, right?
Because he knows they're going to behave in a way that follows who they understand themselves to be before Christ.
And the second half, he's telling them there's a hope, there's an inheritance, and there's a power.
The hope is in the salvation of the Messiah's kingdom, the Messiah, in which that kingdom that Christ says is here.
We're going to go back and look at what Christ says about the kingdom, but he says it's here now.
There's an inheritance in that kingdom.
We're saved and faithful, and therefore predestined for adoption, held in trust, escrow by the Holy Spirit.
And that power can make it happen.
This isn't a fairy tale, he says, because it raised Christ from the dead and moved him to the right hand of God.
And so, you could have a Kent paraphrase of what this says.
He says, you Gentiles who heard the gospel were saved and are now faithful in him,
and now predestined, like the children of Israel, to share in the inheritance,
to have the world blessed through you, because you're adopted as sons into his kingdom,
and you too can share in the hope of God's kingdom.
So glory, right?
Verse 14 just says glory.
So the structure of this book, we call it a book, but it was a letter,
is such that Paul is just burbling forth these thick truths, very densely constructed sentences.
And if you've ever had something you need to tell somebody, I know I've done this.
You need to tell somebody something, but before they can accept thing two,
you have to make sure you agree on thing one, right?
I need to make sure you understand everything that my statement's going to be based on, right?
This is absolutely important that you understand all these things,
and if you do, then thing two is going to make sense to you.
That's the first half and the second half of Ephesians, okay?
Now, a lot of people, if you read it, take it out of context,
it'll look like the first half is a bunch of theology, things you have to believe,
and the second half is a bunch of commandments, things you have to do, right?
And as a result of that, the second half may feel burdensome,
much like the Jewish laws that the Gentiles were so struggling against
as a wall of hostility in their church, right?
So the second half might look like a whole bunch of commands that maybe you don't connect with.
It might look like a bunch of things that you don't really understand.
It doesn't maybe even seem relevant to you.
It definitely doesn't seem possible when you try to follow them
because it's just thing after thing after thing.
The first is way too dense to hear.
The second is way too complicated to follow.
But the truth is that when you find yourself looking at the second and saying,
do I look like that?
Can I believe that?
Do I measure up to that?
Why can't I get this done?
If you focus on the commandments, which are not actually commandments,
they're a description of what you look like once you're living in the kingdom of God.
Once you understand all of that first half to be true,
once you understand your identity and your place,
and that you have an inheritance, you have an ownership.
The early church called it a koinonia, right?
It was our shared endeavor.
Everyone had a shared piece of this.
Once you understand that you have a share in the kingdom,
you're going to act like the second half, right, of the book.
So that means, my mic's coming off.
So that means if you ever come to where you can't follow or connect with the second half,
you don't focus on the second half.
You go back and focus on the first half.
And the second half is the outcome.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So when he says you're adopted as sons, that's a Roman concept.
Why is he using a Roman concept to describe the Hebrew God?
Because who's he talking to?
Gentiles, right.
They don't have any concept of the whole promise of the Messiah.
It's very vague to them.
So he's taking, huia thesia is this, it's a Roman legal construct that allows a father of a household,
pater patras, pater familias, to reach out to anyone in the empire.
You could raise the lowliest slave up to your household.
And they are immediately, they have the rights of adoption.
They have the rights to be protected by the power of the household.
They have the rights to inheritance, just like a born son.
And it's irrevocable once this is called in.
So this is the image that Paul is using.
He's saying, God has destined you for adoption.
And the significance of that is you will now be protected.
You have the power of that household and you will have an inheritance.
And once you know all that about yourself, this is how you're going to behave, right?
You're going to behave in line with the rules of the house.
You're going to want the house to succeed.
You're going to work toward it.
And so that's how the first and the second half flow together.
So it's not saying these are things you should do and things you should believe.
It is saying that if you follow the first half, the second half should be showing up in your life.
And no amount of forcing yourself to care can make you do those things.
It's forcing yourself, it's releasing yourself into the God who forgave you
and have grace to invite you across that gap into adoption in this family, right?
That's how that works.
So that means, for instance, in Ephesians 5.5, it says,
you can be sure that covetous people have no inheritance in the kingdom.
That sounds to us like if I really like my neighbor's car, I'm getting kicked out of heaven, right?
That's what that sounds like.
And it's not what it says.
It's saying if you find yourself just focusing on your neighbor's car, you're not living in the identity of the kingdom of heaven, right?
If you're truly committed to the kingdom of heaven, you just won't be focused on your neighbor's car.
It's that simple, right?
So the causality is backwards.
It's the cause of that.
We need to always keep the full scope of Ephesians in mind as we're reading individual verses.
This letter was written, it appears, at the same time as Philemon and Colossians.
We talked about Philemon up here last summer.
It was a very specific letter written to a very specific person for a very specific problem.
And we're sort of reading over Philemon's shoulder.
And we have to understand everything about what was going on with him to really get the impact of that letter.
Colossians was the church that he was in.
And they were having a lot of troubles, notably this one that Philemon's going through.
So we're still reading a little bit over their shoulder and their specific commands and specific issues they're having in that church that are addressed in that letter.
Both of those are carried by Tychicus, the same guy that we're told is carrying the letter to the Ephesians.
So as he went from church to church and delivered this letter, which doesn't address anybody by name.
It doesn't really call out any specific problems that are being had in any specific church because it's a circular that's sent to all the churches in the area to tell them what it's like in the kingdom of heaven so that the Gentiles will know.
As he's carrying this letter, when he gets to Colossians, he sort of drops off the Colossians letter.
When he gets to Philemon's house, he drops off the Philemon letter, right?
But these are all written at the same time, which is important because it means we can cross-reference them a little bit.
But it also means that this letter was written to Gentiles who had come to believe in the Messiah, the Jewish Messiah, and it's not addressing any particular thing they've done.
It's a general picture.
So who do we know that is a Gentile that's come to believe in the Jewish Messiah?
Yeah, that's right.
Everyone in the room should be raising your hand, right?
It's all of us, right?
So in many ways, more than lots of the other parts of the New Testament, this letter is kind of really written directly to you, right?
You're not having to understand the context of the person that was receiving it as much.
You still need to understand their cultural milieu.
You and I think whoever covers chapter, you know, five and six will talk about how you translate their cultural norms to ours so that you can understand it.
But it really is written to us.
It's telling us how the kingdom of God can work in Winchester as it is in heaven, right?
It's a picture of that.
And what he was telling them over and over is, I know you didn't grow up, because he knew they didn't grow up with the Jewish law or rabbinic teachings or have great familiarity with the Old Testament.
He goes through that flow, those dense sentences of chapter one, two, and three.
And three, incidentally, ends up with a prayer to them.
And so it ends with an amen.
And then chapter four starts with a therefore, because he's saying, with all that in mind, therefore, the second half of the letter.
But he's saying all that because these are people that need to know who they are before God, who they are with God, who God is to them, what the promises mean, what the inheritance is, but don't need to be bothered with the entire Old Testament, right?
Because he's just writing a letter.
So he's describing in non-Jewish words who the God of the Jewish Old Testament is and who he is to them and his Messiah that's come.
As part of that understanding that's replete in the Old Testament, it's clearly found everywhere, is the truth that God is living and active.
And he's interested in discipling and in disciplining and refining and making use of his chosen people to affect the world that they live in.
That's the story of the Old Testament that he's inviting the Ephesians into.
God will use you.
God will ask you to act differently.
God will refine you in your behaviors.
He will make use of you and you will affect the world that you live in.
That footprint of impact is what we call the kingdom of God, right?
That's the sphere, the koinonia that they live in, the shared endeavor, where there's slightly different norms.
That's what we want to have in here in Winchester as it is in heaven.
And like I said earlier, sometimes it's easier to believe in that distant rapture and just stop thinking at that point and saying God will take care of everything.
When you're being invited in to be active, when you read the Lord's Prayer and you say, give us our daily bread, you also need to read Acts 2 where they gave each other their daily bread so that no one was in need, right?
When he says, you know, forgive us our sins, he reminds us that it's not just you receiving forgiveness.
You're being forgiven to the extent that you forgive others, right?
You should be, if you truly have accepted that forgiveness, it's going to be overflowing to the others in your life.
You're going to be affecting the world around you with this forgiveness, this total lack of vengeance.
So, but we still have the question that the Ephesians must have had because it was true then just like it is now.
If the kingdom of God is here and if this is the Messiah's kingdom that's going to change the world, why is the world not changed?
Why do I still see the injustice?
Why did the Messiah not show up and wipe away the bad guys basically?
And we assume when we say that naively that they're the bad guys and we're not, right?
That it's all their bad behavior and I'm great, right?
And we should be grateful that we didn't get wiped away as one of the bad guys.
Instead, we're invited into adoption by his grace into that kingdom.
But nonetheless, let's look at what Christ said about his kingdom.
Just to clarify in our mind what the Ephesians must have understood so that they would accept that the kingdom of God is here, right?
First of all, in, again, the Lord's Prayer, your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven,
clearly draws out for us that we are an active component in this, right?
We're an active part of this.
We have to forgive as we've been forgiven.
We're not just praying for someone to help us.
We're praying that we be involved in that and that he support the good and the success of the good in our lives.
In Mark 1, 14 through 15, John the Baptist had just been arrested because the king's mistress didn't like him
and promised intimacy to the king if he would do what she wanted, right?
So this is a moment of extreme abuse of power and injustice, right?
John is thrown in prison and then beheaded because the king wants more time with his mistress, okay?
That is not the world of the kingdom of God.
And into the midst of that, the next verse, Jesus came saying, the time is fulfilled, the kingdom of God is at hand, repent and believe in the gospel.
How can Jesus declare the kingdom of God is here at that moment?
Why would Mark tell us it at that moment?
Because he's drawn as a clear picture that the kingdom of God does not wipe away the evil.
The kingdom of God invades the evil, right?
He invades the unrighteousness and affects the people one at a time until they melt away and they receive the forgiveness that they can pass on to others.
So it's a very clear picture that the kingdom of God wasn't there confronting.
It wasn't there, but it was there challenging.
He didn't say, would you please consider?
It is a strong directive, you should repent.
You will repent and believe in the gospel as a command, in the plural, to everyone listening, right?
Luke 17, 20 through 21, the Pharisees now are asking Jesus, okay, you said the kingdom of God's here, where is it, right?
The kingdom of God is not coming in ways that can be observed, Jesus answered.
Nor will they say, look, here it is, or there.
For behold, the kingdom of God is in the midst of you.
Now the you there is a plural, and the word he used for in the midst of you, in some of your Bibles it will say among you or within you.
The reason that it's translated oddly is because he's using a singular concept inside you and a plural object, right?
It's inside all of you, right?
It's among you.
So the picture is that the kingdom of God comes into one person and fills an entire community.
And it grows and spreads from person to person, right?
John 18, 36.
Pilate is now accosting Jesus.
He's interrogating him, trying to understand if in fact he's a threat to the Roman Empire.
He says, you know, what are you doing here?
Jesus said, why?
Who told you that?
Or, you know, who told you that I was a king?
And Pilate says, I'm not one of you horrible minorities.
You shut up.
You know, he's kind of rude to him and says, really, what have you done?
Why are you here?
And Jesus says in verse 36, my kingdom is not of this world.
If my kingdom were of this world, my servants would have been fighting that I might not be delivered over to the Jews.
But my kingdom is not from this world.
So we see that the kingdom of God is not just coming and wiping off the planet the injustice.
It's invading that injustice and inviting it to, and commanding it to repent.
It is not visible.
It invades the person and the community.
And it's not political.
It's not here to fight a political battle.
It's not here as a part of any of the struggles we have against each other.
It's here as a footprint from heaven, right?
An outpost of the kingdom of heaven.
So those are the three things Christ clearly says about it.
In the letter of Colossians, which, again, was written at the same time as Ephesians,
Paul has another statement or two that helps enlighten us, give us another perspective on Ephesians.
He says, again, in Colossians 1, 9,
I'm asking that you may be filled with knowledge of his will and all spiritual wisdom and understanding.
Now, what did he say that he wanted to have wisdom and understanding of in Ephesians?
The hope, the inheritance, and the power, right?
And I want you to walk in a manner worthy of the Lord, fully pleasing him, bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in knowledge of God.
What's that knowledge of God?
The hope, the inheritance, and the power, right?
I want to see you bearing fruit, being strengthened with all power, according to his glorious might.
And for homework, if you want to go back and read through the bits of Ephesians and just note all the uses of glory and ask yourself what those are about, that'd be time well spent.
He'll be strengthened with all that power, according to his glorious might, for all endurance and patience and joy.
So, endurance and patience and joy.
This is not a kingdom that struggles and overcomes.
It outlasts.
It endures.
And it endures with patience and joy.
That's what Paul's telling us.
This kingdom of God you're setting up is just going to make it through.
But it's not gritting its teeth and ducking down, and I'm going to make it no matter what.
It's standing up.
It's sharing the command.
And it's with joy spreading the kingdom of God.
Because it's supposed to be, in verse 10, bearing fruit.
We're supposed to have joy giving thanks to the Father who has qualified us to share in the inheritance of the saints and light.
He's delivered us from the domain of darkness and transferred us to this kingdom of his beloved Son,
in whom we have the redemption and the forgiveness of sins.
So, the picture we get in John is of a vine, right?
The kingdom of heaven is a vine.
It grows.
It plants more fruit, which grows, which grows more vines.
And if a branch isn't bearing fruit, it's chopped off, but another one grows, right?
So, while we don't see it now, because it's not visible, it's not of this world,
it's not wiping out the bad guys, right?
It is constantly growing.
In Corinthians, Paul says it's the body of Christ, which is referenced also in Ephesians, right?
That it's a growing thing.
It's an organic thing.
It grows.
And in Ephesians 2.21, he actually speaks of it as a growing building.
Even when he wants to draw the picture of a temple, because we are now the temple,
Christ will dwell in us.
And if someone wants to see Christ and come to worship him, they'll see him in you, right?
Not in the building.
But even when he wants to talk about the picture of the building, he talks about it as a growing building,
because every understanding that the early church had of the kingdom of heaven was that it is nascently planted now when Christ came.
And he planted the church, and it's growing, and it's growing, and it's bearing fruit, and that fruit will grow and bear fruit, right?
That's how the kingdom of God works.
It spreads and grows, and you are a part of it.
It's already seen, but it's not fully realized.
However, we know that, verse 10,
He was made known to us the mystery of his will according to his purpose, which is set forth in Christ as a plan for the fullness of time,
where he will unite all things in him, things in heaven and things on earth.
This kingdom of heaven on earth will be fully realized in the fullness of time.
Ephesians is a letter that explains how that works in practical terms to the people that need to know how to join into it.
Thank goodness, because that's us, right?
So in closing, God plans to reveal his glory through those who are faithful in him.
That's what the letter tells us.
This letter is written to those who are faithful in him.
His kingdom come, his will be done.
God plans to reveal his glory then through you when you're faithful, through your life.
He's chosen us to do this, and he's chosen to do this in a very difficult way because we are inconstant.
We're maybe not as faithful as we want to be.
He's choosing to act with people who are rebellious and who fall away from him and aren't always fruitful.
But he's always there to guard us and to help us grow.
In evaluating how he makes use of our lives, how he invests our life with his will and his purpose and how we commit our lives to him,
we tend to focus on our will, what we will do.
We want to make that second half of this letter happen.
We want to talk about our free will.
We have the option to do this or not, but we've chosen to, some people.
But it's imperative that we focus not on free will, but on his free grace.
Because his grace is over and over what allows us to come back to him and invites us to come back to him and take part in his plan
so that our lives can express his glory in this chaotic and fallen world around us that we are a part of.
And as we come back again and again, asking forgiveness for our faithfulness, our selfishness, our pride.
He will accept us.
We'll be accepted by his grace.
When we humbly accept his grace, which he freely gives us in the character of Christ, we'll grow into the body of Christ.
And the kingdom of God will grow in heaven until, as in verse 10, in the fullness of time, Christ will unite all things in him, in heaven and things on earth.
So this is why we're studying Ephesians for the next five weeks.
Because we want to know how that practically happens in our lives.
And I appreciate all you coming here today.
I appreciate that you're going to read the letter to yourselves this week.
And see you again next week, okay?
Let's close in prayer.
Father God, I thank you so much for the people that have come here to gather in your church.
In the hopes of growing the character of Christ into the body of Christ.
That we will yield to you.
We will accept your grace in the small things.
That we will diminish our own wills so that you can become greater in our lives and into the lives of the people around us.
Pray that you would show us in small ways how to make that happen this week.
And give us moments when, painful though it may be, we can release the pride and our own desires.
And have a moment where we overflow your grace to the world around us.
Overflow your forgiveness, specifically, to the world around us.
Thank you, in Jesus' name, amen.